In the heart of London, some very
special paintings are on the move.
And History Hit [music] has
behind-the-scenes access.
A new exhibition is opening.
An exhibition [music] that brings us up
close with six extraordinary Tudor
women.
Who all had one thing in common.
King Henry VIII.
When you're thinking of the Tudors, it's
hard to escape this fellow. And that was
particularly true for the six wives.
>> [music]
>> We even think of them according to this
little rhyme about how he disposed of
them.
And the six women who had the misfortune
of being married to Henry have been
reimagined and reinvented for every
century since. Here's a Victorian
picture from the 1870s. It shows the
arrest of Anne Boleyn in a rather
romantic fashion. [music] We've had
novels. We've had films. We've had all
sorts of ways of considering the wives,
even recently in a stage musical.
But here at this exhibition at the
National Portrait Gallery in London, we
want to think about them as six
individuals. Here we have a chance to
think about how the women wanted to be
seen themselves.
Six women who led distinct lives, who
chose how they wanted to be portrayed,
shaping their memory.
And they've left us with the chance to
look at them again with the benefit of
all the hindsight of history.
I'm joining exhibition curator Dr.
Charlotte Bolland.
We're starting with the first woman
[music] to marry Henry, Catherine of
Aragon.
Charlotte, this portrait is rarely seen
like this alone. Why is that?
>> Well, I think this is um so interesting
because this really is about how do you
present yourself as queen and the key
areas that you can see are through
clothing and jewels. So, it's um
Catherine's status is evident um in this
extraordinary amount of uh cloth of gold
that she has um visible here. The cloth
of gold was restricted by sumptuary law
to be worn by the king and the immediate
family and then the large number of
pearls, these red stones in her um
English uh head dress. So, her
magnificence is projected through her
clothing.
>> What should we know about the production
of portraits for the royals at this
time?
>> This is really at the kind of beginning
of painted portraiture being produced in
England. That idea of producing
portraits to kind of assert your
authority at home domestically in your
spaces, that that is something that's
quite new in Henry VIII's reign and this
is really the beginning of that period.
Um and it's interesting to think about
kind of what Catherine's role might have
been in that because she obviously in
coming from the Spanish court that
portraiture was more prevalent there.
And I think it is interesting that the
um records that we have, there is a
reference to a paired portrait of
Catherine with Henry in Baynard's Castle
in the house of the Queen Consort that
Henry had granted to her on the Thames.
So, it's interesting to think whether
Catherine might have been a bit of a
driving force in the production of
portraiture in England.
>> This portrait is one of those pictures
that is rarely seen alone.
And is it because it is actually one of
a pair?
>> Yes, so that this is um normally
displayed alongside a portrait of uh
Henry VIII which while not being um a
literal pair of objects, the composition
and format suggest that they were
intended to be created as a pair with
other um portrait types of Henry and
Catherine. And indeed that reference to
um the inventory at Baynard's Castle is
of the portrait of Henry and Catherine.
And I think during um this moment in
their reign that it is all about their
sort of paired authority. H's and K's
are everywhere. Um kind of Mars and
Venus. It's complementary male and
female power. And so that idea of having
Catherine's portrait paired with
Henry's.
>> We don't know if Catherine commissioned
this painting, though she would
certainly [music] have chosen what she
wore, how she projected herself.
But there are other far smaller pictures
of her in the exhibition.
>> [music]
>> Miniatures. They were probably made
specifically for Catherine.
>> For me, this is when the portraits start
to get really exciting.
And tiny.
>> [laughter]
>> So, can we talk about these two
miniatures of Catherine of Aragon? What
do we know about their making? Who made
them? Who ordered them?
>> Well, so these are
two completely fascinating um objects
that are really from the beginning of a
new art form um in England, which is
miniature painting.
And I think it's [music] so fascinating
that in these two objects we can see how
Catherine of Aragon is at the kind of
forefront of that moment of the
development of this new art form.
>> But as well as being a new type of
painting, like many portraits from this
period, one of these miniatures contains
some [music] carefully pointed messages
at a critical moment in Catherine's
life.
In the mid-1520s.
When her marriage was starting to
unravel.
>> So we've got one here on the left, which
has a Latin inscription that says
um
Queen Catherine, his wife.
What do you read into that?
>> Well, so again, it seems to be this idea
that
this is a paired object, that it is kind
of half an inscription, that clearly
there was an image of Henry VIII, the
husband, um that this image was kind of
paired with. And uh there are references
in uh jewelry inventories to um paired
portraits of Henry and Catherine in
tablets.
>> And that's important, isn't it? Because
the one of Henry gives us a clue about
the date of this miniature. What does it
tell us?
>> Exactly. That there's a group of these
>> [music]
>> portrait miniatures of Henry that say
that he's in his 35th year. And so that
is aged 34. And so between [music] 1526
and 1527. And so the kind of key
transformational moment in [music]
Catherine and Henry's marriage.
>> That suggests to me at least that Henry
wouldn't have been commissioning a pair
of portraits of himself and Catherine at
that time.
So does that
suggest do you think that it's Catherine
who's paying for these?
>> I think that's very
plausible. And then particularly if you
think about the way that she's chosen to
present herself in this miniature
because that's the one moment where sort
of you can see the queen's
decision-making in action is what
they're choosing to wear and in their
clothes and their jewels. And in this
portrait of Catherine, she looks very
different from the Catherine who is sort
of familiar to all of us from later 16th
century copies of her portrait that are
much more English in style. And you can
see in the portrait of her displayed
alongside that here she's wearing very
different fashions.
>> Yes, so here we've got Spanish [music]
clothing. And actually and even the
cross itself is something that her
mother wore but that sort of style of
cross cuz it's associated with the
observant Franciscans.
>> [music]
>> So everything about this speaks of her
Hispanic heritage.
>> Catherine was the daughter of Ferdinand
and Isabella, [music]
monarchs who had united Spain, which
made her part of an enormously
influential family that dominated much
of Europe.
>> And we know that there are moments when
Catherine very sort of self-consciously
presented herself because in her Spanish
heritage and her relation to the
Habsburgs that she is a member of the
most powerful family in Europe and that
her
uh
Charles V kind of rules half of
Europe. And so, I think this really kind
of demonstrates her um
her heritage and the power that comes
from that.
>> So often we have this kind of inflated
sense of Henry VIII,
but actually, that's such an important
reminder that it's Catherine who comes
from this all powerful dynasty. And by
wearing Spanish clothes, she's saying,
"Wait a second, remember who his wife
is. Remember who you're messing with."
>> Exactly. It's a very kind of um
sort of bold proclamation of her status
as as his wife and that um
her
imagery in that that she is not someone
to be kind of underestimated. And I
think that's something that Catherine
could uniquely call upon this kind of
European um support power structure that
not only was with her nephew um Charles
V, but also had various relations with
uh Margaret of Austria, and then also to
the Pope um
through her kind of families' power. So,
she's really displaying the fact that
she has allies.
>> And Margaret of Austria is an important
point because the painters, we we don't
know exactly who the painters are, but
they had come from Margaret of Austria's
court, isn't that right?
>> Exactly. So, the the miniature develops
in England with this um fascinating
family, the Horenbout family, um who uh
the father, Gerard, had uh worked um
at Margaret of Austria's um course as a
[music] um
illuminator of manuscripts.
>> Gerard Horenbout was a gifted painter
and the head of a family of exceptional
miniaturists.
>> He comes to England uh with his son
Lucas and daughter Susanna, um all of
whom are uh recognized as artists, um
and Lucas appears regularly in the kind
of King's um payments. But, it's still a
very live research question of kind of
unpicking the hands of Gerard, Lucas,
and Susanna within [music] this group of
early miniatures, but it's very um elite
royal patronage that they're kind of
right in the um at the heart of the
court.
>> The highly skilled Horenbouts were well
able to convey the clear, detailed
messages that Catherine wanted to
express.
>> She's probably commissioning, [music]
she's choosing what she's wearing to
proclaim her power, and in case anyone's
not wondering what's happening in
1526-27,
it's exactly the time that Anne Boleyn's
come onto the scene, and a year after
her only daughter, Mary,
has been sort of diminished in status
because
Henry's illegitimate son has been raised
to the dukedom. [music]
So, it's quite the moment to be making
this statement.
>> Exactly. And thinking about who might
have received this
>> [music]
>> um miniature, who was she sort of uh
speaking to? Because that's the thing
that miniatures are very portable. So,
whether that question, is it for her
kind of internal alliance or her
external kind of allies?
>> So, here we have a miniature, very
likely commissioned by Catherine
herself, that she could carry on her
[music] person or easily send to people.
A picture with a strong, combative
message. I am the wife of the king and a
woman with power in my own right.
It was almost certainly [music] paired
with miniatures of Henry that she
commissioned. Portable portraits that
Henry appears to have used for his own
romantic purposes as he pursued Anne
Boleyn.
>> [music]
>> Interestingly, we know that Henry sends
a picture in a bracelet, which suggests
it's very small, to Anne Boleyn along
with those love letters. And I've always
wondered if he's actually sending her
one of the miniatures that Catherine has
had commissioned.
>> Yeah, he's a scumbag.
>> [laughter]
>> Exactly. I mean, that's um such a kind
of horrifying thought in a way, but it's
um very plausible that in that kind of
patronage of artists and the creation of
multiples that then having the sort of
freedom to do with these images as he
wished, and so to yes, pass them
onwards.
>> Despite [music] Catherine's efforts, we
all know what happened next. Henry
married again, and had his marriage to
his Spanish wife annulled.
>> Some of these [music] paintings are so
familiar. I don't need to tell you that
this is Anne Boleyn.
But it's familiar, and yet we're on
shaky ground, because this was not
painted during Anne's lifetime. It was
painted [music] during the reign of her
daughter Elizabeth. It may be based on a
lost original, or it may be that we've
got obsessed with the bee with the
pendant.
>> [music]
>> We all know the bee pendant with the
pearls, and yet maybe it was a creation.
>> [music]
>> Maybe Anne never wore [clears throat]
it.
But we can tell about some details of
the pictures of her successors [music]
that indicate to us choices that they
made, things that they chose to wear to
signal a certain message.
To explore these messages captured in
paint, I'm moving on to two very
different [music] pictures in this
exhibition, paintings of the woman who
rose as Anne [music] fell.
Jane Seymour.
This painting of Jane Seymour is a copy
of a picture prepared [music]
in 1536. It wasn't commissioned by Jane,
but Jane has [music] chosen what she's
wearing, these incredibly rich clothes,
but also the jewels that she's wearing.
The one I'm particularly [music]
interested in is this one, IHS, the
first three letters of the name of Jesus
in Greek, [music]
where we see it before, on Catherine of
Aragon.
And we know [music] that Jane was in
Catherine's service,
and we know from her actions as queen
that [music] she was a Catholic in
faith. She acted to try and restore the
monasteries, or to at least stop their
dissolution and to keep a nunnery
together.
And [music] she put Princess Mary back
at the heart of the court. And I think
that [music] in this picture we see Jane
signaling that.
But we see it somewhere else as well.
Like Catherine of Aragon, [music]
telling miniatures survive of Jane.
This is a miniature [music] from 1536
the year that Jane becomes queen.
And here we have her choosing to wear
the tau, [music] the T-shaped cross.
Just as Catherine of [music] Aragon had
done.
In every picture of Jane, in other
words, she has this quiet signaling
[music] of her allegiance, of her faith,
of the things that she believes in, even
whilst it looks like [music] we're just
seeing a picture of a queen.
When it comes to portraiture, we expect
[music]
to see their character.
And we can, but not in their faces.
Because
whilst some of these pictures were
commissioned by the queens,
>> [music]
>> many of them weren't. But they were
choosing what they would look like.
They're choosing their form of
self-fashioning, self-presentation.
[music]
They're choosing the subtle messages
that are there to be read by those in
the know.
Jane Seymour died shortly after what
should have been her moment of glory.
The birth of her son by Henry, the
eventual Edward the Sixth. [music]
But Jane didn't only leave behind an
heir.
She left [music] a record, a picture of
her beliefs.
Jane Seymour used her portraits, her to
indicate her political and religious
affiliations. Anne of Cleves, who we
have here, used her dress to tell us
about her character.
This is a picture by Bartholomäus Bruyn
the Elder,
>> [music]
>> and it's one of what possibly two
pictures that were sent during the
negotiations for Henry [music] VIII to
marry Anne of Cleves. It shows her in
her Netherlandish dress holding a
carnation, which is a symbol of
betrothal. [music]
And
Henry didn't like it. He wanted to see
her through Holbein's eyes.
But the picture itself has messages for
us. Not only does it give us an idea of
[music]
the fashion that she was used to, these
huge puff sleeves and the high neck and
the stickelchen, which is the seated
headdress.
But also, we've got this silk
a band across her head, which has a
motto [music] on it, "A bon fin" or "A
bonne fin".
So, Anne of Cleves is deliberately
choosing to wear [music] something with
this motto on. What does it mean? It
means to a good end.
And I [music] think it says something
about her character, because we know
that she will go on to be someone who
accepts [music]
the difficult situation she's put in,
who accepts becoming the king's sister.
And this speaks to her [music] sense of
stoicism, her sense of Christian hope,
that she knows that she's moving to a
good end, and [music] she accepts what
comes.
>> What came was a rapid divorce, but then
a long and relatively peaceful
retirement in which Anne, the ex-wife,
was now given the official status of the
king's sister.
I'm moving on now to a very different
woman. The sixth of these lives,
>> [music]
>> Catherine Parr.
A fascinating woman who is far too often
dismissed as a dull footnote.
It's time to take a closer look.
>> Wow, I mean this one is just glorious,
isn't it, Charlotte?
>> Yes, so this is one of the treasures of
the National Portrait Gallery's
collection of Tudor portraits. Um, it's
an amazing full-length portrait of
Catherine Parr.
>> And what can we read into the
iconography of this, of her
self-presentation?
>> Well, this is so interesting in its
scale. So, this is the um earliest
[music] known full-length portrait of an
English queen. Um, and so she is there
in her magnificence, this extraordinary
um cloth of silver and um embroidered
cloth of gold gown that she's wearing
with these links fur sleeves.
The number of uh diamonds that she's
wearing and pearls.
Fabulous cameo [music] um pendants.
>> That jewel. Now, that's how it was
identified, wasn't it?
>> It one of the kind of um
intriguing kind of frustrations with
Catherine Parr is that she was the queen
who was by far the most interested in
portraiture and very proactively
commissioning her portraits.
>> [music]
>> And yet, soon after her death, her
iconography became confused, her
likeness became so detached from her
story. And so, um because she didn't
have uh children to kind of continue um
her commemoration and her family
similarly kind of fell in uh status. So,
these images of her got lost and this
portrait for a long time was confused
with an image of her ward, Lady Jane
Grey.
>> And it was only in the identification of
the jewel that she's wearing in an
inventory um that kind of reaffirmed her
status of being actually a portrait of
Catherine Parr.
>> And that's interesting on so many
levels. It's interesting because she's
the one written off as the dowdy old
widow and actually she's confused with a
16-year-old. But also, that she's so
active in creating this legacy or or
patronizing artists and you know,
writers and other people to [music]
produce things like this. And yet that's
forgotten. People weren't looking to
tell her story in the
late 16th, early 17th century. They were
more interested in Lady Jane Grey as a
kind of Protestant heroine, Protestant
martyr.
>> [music]
>> And so, in looking for an appropriate
image of Lady Jane Grey, they kind of
appropriated Catherine Parr's. And it
wasn't until the sort of 17th century
and an idea of wanting to tell histories
of Britain
and and to
>> [music]
>> gather together the queen's portraits in
a set Henry and you needed all six
wives, that suddenly
historians and artists were casting
around like, "Oh, where where's
Catherine Parr gone? Where have her
images gone?" And so, all sorts of
different source images are used [music]
to kind of create an iconography of
Catherine Parr while it was sort of
hiding in plain sight there in numerous
numerous prints and paintings called
Lady Jane Grey.
>> Catherine was trusted to be regent when
Henry was away on campaign [music] in
1544.
And she was the first English queen to
write a book in her own name, Prayers
and Meditations.
The exhibition also has a spectacular
long thought lost painting
>> [music]
>> that speaks volumes about this woman and
her independent mind.
>> This painting, which [music] is produced
towards the end of Catherine Parr's
reign or possibly even just after
Henry's [music] death,
and in this she is celebrated in all her
queenly magnificence. [music] That this
is a fabulous portrait that was long
thought to have been lost in a fire. It
has recently been conserved. So, [music]
displayed here for the first time kind
of in dialogue with all these other
portraits of Catherine. That we see here
the jewel again emerging kind of
identifying her with these [music] black
stones all being diamonds that the
fashion was to black back diamonds with
the black foil for their luster rather
than their sparkle.
So, you can really see quite how
extravagantly [music] Catherine is
saying her status from all the pearls,
all the diamonds, and amazing gold and
pearl and diamond-studded headdress.
Actually, it's kind of insane, isn't it?
If you look at the number of diamonds
she's wearing and the size of them. I
mean, these are huge. And that's before
you even talk about the the sable fur
and the embroidery and the cloth of
silver tissue and all the the rest of
it. I mean, this speaks of an
unparalleled status at the time.
>> And that's one thing that the queens
proclaim through their portraits, that
the Tudors have a very literal
understanding [music] of magnificence.
It is how much wealth are you wearing?
And the amount that Catherine is wearing
in this is quite um extraordinary.
>> Catherine was Henry's wife during the
perilous final years of his reign.
She was a committed Protestant when
Henry would not countenance many such
beliefs.
There was even a warrant for her arrest
at one point.
But she survived.
And if you look even closer, she has
left us clues about her inner thoughts.
>> But I think there is one uh sort of tiny
detail that says something really
fascinating about her self-presentation.
And [music] that's in these jewels, her
bracelets just peeking out from her
undersleeves, which if you look really
closely, you can see written on these uh
jewels [music] in enamel work, "Laus
Deus."
>> And "Laus Deus" is so interesting
because it's
ungrammatical Latin at one level. And we
know that she spoke Latin. So, "Laus
Deus" doesn't mean [music] praise be to
God, which people might think it means.
It comes from a verse in the Latin
Vulgate, which says, "Tibi silens
[music] laus Deus." So,
"Remaining silent, praise to you, oh
God." And it's precisely what she's
doing. So, she might be ostentatiously
showing off her magnificence, but
silently, quietly, she is praising God
while this is done. And that speaks to
her as a a person who's hiding her
beliefs late in Henry's life.
>> Exactly, that this is the kind of moment
where she's narrowly survived the
attempts to kind of undermine her
position which you know carried the real
sort of [music] threat of trial and
execution for heresy that the stakes
were so high and as had been
demonstrated by the experience of you
know her predecessors as queen queens
were disposable queens could be executed
so there was no sense that being a queen
could offer any protection. And so I
think it's so fascinating that this
small little detail about praising God
but in silence at the moment when
Catherine has had to kind of repress her
own views personally and has kind of
survived her [music] marriage by
pleading forgiveness from Henry and
saying that she will never dare to
advise him on matters of religion in the
future and that she definitely has her
public face at court is reduced in a way
towards the end of Henry's reign that
from her kind of high point of Henry
going off on campaign in 1544 and she's
kind of publishing books to support his
campaign
commissioning all sorts of portraits
that then that the kind of threat of
death and execution for heresy that
she's much kind of a quieter figure
towards the end of Henry's reign.
But yet is choosing in this portrait to
really present that she's still there
that she is still thinking and is
composing at the same time is you know
writing this personal
tract of personal devotion in the
lamentation of a sinner which is then
published shortly after Henry's death.
>> So what's fascinating is that we are
standing in front of a painting that was
almost certainly being painted at the
time that she was writing that
Protestant book in secret to publish
after Henry's death and yet
she can't resist
having a reference to her faith in this
picture.
>> Yes it's so
it's so fascinating and it goes to show
kind of what those tiny details are that
in portraits that can provide such kind
of insight into the way the queens
presented themselves that we always want
to kind of try and read character onto
portraits and to try and meet these
people to use them to cross time.
But the clues are often other and other
kinds of details that there's that
mediated encounter through the artist.
But what are the bits that the queens
had control over that they would be
wanting the audience to see?
>> That's exactly it. So we think we're
meeting their face, but actually we're
meeting with their mind.
When we see these portraits gathered
together in one place, we are having an
amazing encounter [music] with the women
of the 16th century.
It's an incredible opportunity to look
at and read their pictures, their
personalities, and their beliefs.
And get closer
to the real people they were.
>> [music]
[music]